BU Records: Beall-Russell Lectures, Inclusive: 1975-2013, undated, Bulk: 1982-1999, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Beall-Russell Lectures
Inclusive: 1975-2013, undated, Bulk: 1982-1999, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/209
Baylor University
5 document boxes
BU Records: Beall-Russell Lectures contains materials relating to lectures at Baylor University beginning in 1982. The collection deals with the behind-the-scenes work for the lectures, including correspondence with speakers and committee members, financial and marketing decisions, and information relating to the speaker selection process.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Biography/Profile
The Beall-Russell Lectures are a series of lectures given at Baylor University beginning in 1982 and continuing up to today. The lectures are based in the humanities and cover topics such as history, politics, poetry, and literature. The lectures began after an endowment from Virginia B. Ball, a graduate of Baylor University. She had the series named after her mother Mrs. John A. Beall and the former dean of women at Baylor, Lily Russell. Ball was a philanthropist who focused on both education and the environment. She was among the founding board members for the Indiana Board of Humanities, served as the trustee emeritus of the Interlochen Center for the Arts, and served as the first female member of the National Wildlife Federation board. She passed away in 2005.
Scope and Content
BU Records: Beall-Russell Lectures contains materials from 1975-2013. The materials reflect the behind-the-scenes work of the lecture's faculty committee when it comes to speaker selection, finances, and marketing for the event.
There are six series within this collection. Series I. Correspondence contains letters between the committee and those outside of Baylor such as Virginia B. Ball. Series II. Committee Files contains materials relating to daily work of the committee itself like inter-personal correspondence and meeting minutes. Series III. Financial Records contains materials such as budgets, expense reports, and contracts. Series IV: Literary Productions contains marketing materials such as posters, booklets, brochures. Series V: Speaker Information contains materials relating to individual speakers such as biographies, correspondence, and transcripts of their speeches. Series VI: Audio-Visual Materials contains VHS tapes and DVD's of speaker's lectures.
Arrangement
Prior to processing, the collection was housed in labeled and unlabeled folders in no apparent arrangement. While some folders were labeled by date, the majority of folders were labeled by subject. For the current round of processing, some materials of the same topic were grouped together,
Currently, this collection includes six series: I. Correspondence, II. Committee Files, III. Financial Records, IV. Literary Productions, V. Speaker Information, and VI. Audio-Visual.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/209. Acquired 1983-01-00
Related Resources
Related references
“About Beall-Russell.” Beall-Russell Lectures in the Humanities - Baylor University. Baylor University. Accessed 2019 September 25.
Becker, Brittany. “Beall-Russell Lectures in the Humanities.” Wacoan.com. Wacoan Magazine. Accessed 2019 September 25.
“Virginia B. Ball.” Edmund Virginia Ball Foundation. Edmund Virginia Ball Foundation. Accessed 2019 September 25.
Index Terms
Subjects
DVDs.; History.; Humanities.; Lectures and lecturing -- Texas -- Waco.; Literature; Philosophy; Transcripts.; VHS.
Genres
Business correspondence.; Financial records.; Lectures.; Minutes (Records); Personal correspondence.; Promotional materials.
- Correspondence, 1982-2009; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence between the Beall-Russell Lectures committee and those outside of the university. In particular, these letters include those to Virginia B. Ball who financially endowed the lectures. The condition of the series is excellent.
  - Committee Correspondence, 1982-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Ball Correspondence, 1998-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Committee Files, 1982-2013, undated; 2
  This series contains the files from the Beall-Russell Lectures committee. These files include correspondence between committee members, meetings from minutes, and event information. The condition of the series is excellent.
  - Committee Files, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee Files, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Committee Files, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committee Files (1 of 2), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Committee Files (2 of 2), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Committee Files, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Committee Files, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Committee Files, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Committee Files, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Committee Files, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Committee Files, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Committee Files, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Committee Files, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committee Files, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Committee Files, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Committee Files, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Financial Records, 1983-2011; 3
  General condition: Good.
  The series contains the financial records of the Beall-Russell Lectures. These include budget and expense reports, budget comparisons, and contracts. The condition of the series is good.
  - Budget Comparisons (1 of 2), 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Budget Comparisons (2 of 2), 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Detail Budget Reports, 2000-2011 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Contracts, 2004-2011 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Expense Reports, 2002-2011 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Literary Productions, 1982-2013; 4
  This series contains all the promotional materials for the Beall-Russell Lectures. This include posters, brochures, and booklets. The condition of the series is excellent.
  - Lecture Booklets, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lecture Booklets, 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lecture Booklets, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lecture Booklets, 2003-2008 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lecture Brochures, 1982-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lecture Brochures, 2000-2013 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Lecture Posters, 1998-2013 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Speaker Information, 1975-2010, undated; 5
  This series contains information relating to the speakers of the Beall-Russell Lectures. These include the speaker's curia vita, transcripts of speeches, and biographies. The condition of the series is excellent.
  - A.S. Byatt, 1992-1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bill Moyers, 1991-1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bryce Lyon, 1988-1989, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Carlos Fuentes, 1975-1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Czeslaw Milosz, 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Dana Gioia, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - David N. Cannadine, 1998-1999, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Edward W. Said, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Frederick Crosson, 2001, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Harry Seiber, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Helen Hennessy Vendler, 1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - James MacGregor Burns, 1984, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - James Burker, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Linda Colley, 1999-2000, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Robert Hass, 1999-2000, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Robert Rosenblum, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Robert Hughes, 1987, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Martha Nussbaum, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Michael Mayne, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Mortimer Adler, 1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Richard Marius, 1985-1986, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Richard Rorty, 1983-1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Shelby Foote, 2002, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - William H. McNeill, 1991-1992, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Audio-Visual, 1998-2012; 6
  This series contains the audio-visual materials from the Beall-Rusell Lectures. This include VHS tapes and DVDs of the lectures. The condition of the series is excellent.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Compact disk (CD); Digital video disk (DVD); Video home system (VHS) tapes
  - Baylor University 1998 Beall-Russell Humanities Festival Bill Moyers (Item 1)
  - Baylor University 1998 Beall-Russell Humanities Festival Dr. Edward Said (Item 2)
  - Fall 2001 Beall-Russell Dr. Fred Crosson "Seeing and Believing: Education and Faith" (Item 3)
  - Shelby Foot Lecture, 2002 (Item 4)
  - Faith and Evil Elanore Stump, 2003 (Item 5)
  - Azar Nafasi Beall-Russell Lecture, 2006 (Item 6)
  - 2010 Beall-Russell Lecture in the Humanities - Dana Gioia "Why Culture Matter" (Item 7)
  - Beall-Russell Lecture in the Humanities - John Patrick Shanley, 2011 (Item 8)
  - The Beall-Russell Lecture in the Humanities - Anne Fadiman "Bacon as Bookmarks: Engrossed in the Love of Reading", 2012 (Item 9)
  - Beall-Russell Lectures in the Humanites - Timothy Egan "The Worst of Times', 2013 (Item 10)